Guide to the Luell W. Guthrie Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Luell W. Guthrie papers
1934-1987
SC0329
Guthrie, Luell W.
2.5 Linear feet
Guthrie's professional papers pertain to her teaching and administrative duties, her professional associations, and her interests in women's sports, particularly tennis; included are correspondence, minutes, memoranda, reports, newsletters, brochures, and other printed items. Of note is correspondence concerning the issue of competition in women's sports; the issue of physical education becoming co-educational at Stanford; and the minutebook of the Stanford Women's Tennis Club. Her personal papers include a paper she wrote while a student at the University of Washington; itineraries and other records from her travels; materials relevant to her year of service with the American Red Cross, including her letters to her parents; and photographs.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gifts of Luell Weed Guthrie, 1979-1987.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Luell Weed Guthrie, a leader in women's intercollegiate tennis, taught physical education classes at Stanford University from 1936 until her retirement in 1972 and served as director of the Women's Physical Education Department from 1956 to 1968. She received her a.b. in physical education from the University of Washington in 1931 and her M.A. from the Teachers College, Columbia University, in 1936. During World War II, she took a year's leave of absence from Stanford to assist the director of personnel for the American Red Cross.
Description of the Collection
Guthrie's professional papers pertain to her teaching and administrative duties, her professional associations, and her interests in women's sports, particularly tennis; included are correspondence, minutes, memoranda, reports, newsletters, brochures, and other printed items. Of note is correspondence concerning the issue of competition in women's sports; the issue of physical education becoming co-educational at Stanford; and the minutebook of the Stanford Women's Tennis Club. Her personal papers include a paper she wrote while a student at the University of Washington; itineraries and other records from her travels; materials relevant to her year of service with the American Red Cross, including her letters to her parents; and photographs.
Access Terms
American Red Cross.; Guthrie, Luell W.; Stanford University. Department of Athletics, Physical Education and Recreation.; Stanford University. Department of Athletics.; Stanford Women's Tennis Club.; Photoprints.; Sports for women.; Tennis.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Professional papers:
    - Academic Council, 1944-48, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Activities, Women's Physical Education (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Administration of Physical Education (ED 175), 1962 - course materials (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Alumni Association - Athletic fashion show 1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - American Association for Health, Physical Education and Recreation, 1950-71 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Assorted brochures and publications (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Classes and majors, Fall 1951 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence 1941-43 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence 1956-59 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence 1960-64 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence - Mary Yost 1941-47 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Departmental miscellany (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Departmental records Fall 1968 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Departmental records Spring 1969 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Departmental records Fall 1969 (1) (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Departmental records Fall 1969 (2) (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Dyment, Bertha - obituary and memorial notes (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Elementary School Physical Education (ED 157) - lesson plans (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Extramurals, 1962-63 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Extramurals, 1963-69 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Future of the School of Education at S.U. - report, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Grade study, P.E. courses, 1953-58 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Library Committee, School of Education (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Major course of study (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Mechanics of movement - bibliography, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - National Association for Physical Education of College Women, 1939, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - PAC 8 Tennis, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Physical Education - co-ed department at S.U., 1970 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Physical Education majors (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Physical Education majors (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Physical Education Program evaluation (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Policies (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Proposed P.E. minors (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Reports and papers by other authors (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Santa Clara County unit of California Association of Health, Physical Education and Recreation, 1940-42 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Santa Clara County unit of California Association of Health, Physical Education and Recreation - Institute, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - School of Health - committees, 1941-45 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Sports Day - planning outline (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Staff meetings (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Stanford Ski Club (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Stanford Ski Club - emblem (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - “Co-recreational Skiing in Colleges and Universities” (pamphlet by Luell A. Weed [Guthrie]) 1947 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Stanford Women's Tennis Club, minutes, 1934-52 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Summer recreation, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Summer recreation - swimming report 1953 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Summer recreation, 1957-58 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Summer recreation, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Summer recreation, 1961-71 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Tennis 182 (tournament organization) (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Tennis tournaments draw sheets (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Tennis Umpires Association - history by L. Guthrie, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Triangular Sports Day, Mills College, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Winter sports (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Personal Papers:
    - Berta Gray - information concerning (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Clippings (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Christmas cards from F. Terman and family, 1973-76 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous items (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Obituaries of friends and colleagues (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Student paper "The sound value of play and games," University of Washington (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Travel records, 1965-79 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Travel records, 1981-87 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - University of Washington alumni newsletter, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Photographs - dogs (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Photographs - dry-skiing classes (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Photographs - people (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Photographs - Red Cross work (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Photographs - Stanford women's gymnasium (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Photographs - tennis (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Photographs - travel (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Photographs - negatives (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Scrapbook of clippings, photographs, postcards, memorabilia, and her letters to her parents pertaining to her work with the Red Cross, 1943-44 (Box 4 os, Folder 1)
    - Scrapbook of clippings, photographs, postcards, programs, and memorabilia pertaining to her association with Stanford University, 1936-40 (Box 4 os, Folder 2)